Azurus opens the
books and reviews the deeds of the
righteous. And it is that review of the
deeds of the righteous that will
reverse what the little horn had
planned. I'm sorry. What Hmon had
planned. It will
reverse people talking about they're
afraid of the judgment. Listen to me you
guys. It is the review of the
books that is in favor of God's people.
Daniel 7:9 and 10. I beheld till thrones
were cast down and the ancient of days
did sit whose garment was white as snow
and the hair of his head like the pure
wool. His throne was like the fiery
flame and his wheels as burning fire.
A fiery stream issued and came forth
from before him. Thousand thousands
ministered unto him and 10,000 times
10,000 stood before him. The judgment
was set and the books were
opened. Why does God bring Daniel into
the palace of Shushan, which is most
likely not even standing when Daniel has
his vision? Why does God supernaturally
take Daniel into this place, this palace
of the future king Ahazurus where he's
going to open books and review
characters and review deeds and
overturn? Why? Because all because of
the intercession of this woman who goes
in on behalf of her
people to intercede on their behalf.
Esther 6:3-5, we're almost done, y'all.
We are almost done. And the king said,
"What honor and dignity has been done to
Mori for this?" Then said the king's
servants that ministered unto him,
"There is nothing done for him." And the
king said, "Who is in the court?" Now
Hmon was come into the outward court of
the king's house to speak unto the king
to hang Mordei on the gallows that he
had prepared for him. And the king's
servant said unto him, "Behold, Hmon
standeth in the court." And the king
said, "Let him come in." And y'all know
the rest of the story. The king said
unto Azeras or the king Azarus said unto
Let me pause. Let me pause. Come back.
Let's let's let's get off the
screen. So the judgment reverses what
was going to happen to Mori. Mori is
blessed instead of killed. And then
Esther reveals the plot of Hmon to the
king. And I want you to watch what
happens in verse se chapter 7 verse 5
and 6. Then King Azerus answered and
said unto Esther the queen, "Who is he
and where is he that dur presume in his
heart to do so?" And Esther said, "The
adversary,
Satan, the adversary and an enemy is
this wicked Hmon." Then Hmon was afraid
before the king and the queen. And you
know what happens next,
right? Do you do you guys know what
happens next?
What happens
next is that Hmon is
killed. Why is this so
interesting? In Leviticus 16 7 and 8,
talking about the day of atonement, the
day of judgment, there were lots
cast. There were lots that were cast. In
Leviticus 16:7, the Bible says, "And he
shall take the two goats and present
them before the Lord at the door of the
tabernacle of the congregation. And
Aaron shall cast lots upon the two
goats, one lot for the Lord
Mordei. One lot for the Lord and the
other lot for the skate
goats. Yes,
y'all. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
See, when these lots are cast, the the
the thing that was supposed to destroy
Mori ended up destroying
Hmon. The weapon that was supposed to be
turned on Mori ends up destroying Hmon.
This is what the judgment does you
guys. In this on the day of atonement,
two lots were cast. One for the Lord,
the other for the scapegoat. The
scapegoat will ultimately
suffer and ultimately be
punished because of the judgment.
In other words, beloved, the story of
Esther, the story of what happened in
the palace at
Shushan has
direct relevance to what is happening in
Daniel chapter 8.
A king on a throne with books, a
judgment, lots being
cast, the
reversal, the
reversal of that which was meant to
destroy God's people now being the means
by which they are delivered.
And this is where the Jews established
the feast of Purim, the celebration of
Purim. Let's go to the screen. We're
almost done here. We got just a few more
slides. This verse records the
establishment of the f of the feast of
Purim, commemorating the Jews
deliverance from Hmon's plot of
extermination. The celebration was
instituted as an annual memorial to
remind future generations of God's
providential care. After the dramatic
reversal of fortune where Hmon was
executed on the very gallows he had
prepared for Mori, the Jews were granted
permission by King Azerus to defend
themselves against their enemies. Their
victory over those who sought to destroy
them transformed the days intended for
their destruction into days of triumph.
So many of us see the judgment of God as
a thing that is supposed to destroy us
when beloved, it is a thing that is
designed to deliver us from the
enemy. Come on
y'all. The name Purum comes from the
Persian word purr, meaning lot. It's on
the screen. Referring to how Hmon had
cast lots to determine the day for
destroying the Jews. What began as a
scheme for annihilation became a
celebration of deliverance marked by
four key elements. One, feasting
together in communal joy. Two, sending
gifts of food. Three, giving charable.
Four, reading the story of Esther. This
joyous festival continues to be
celebrated by the Jews worldwide. It is
a reminder of God's protective hand over
his people. Beloved, the judgment is
about God's vindication of his people.
Note the parallels. a death decree in
the end times paralleling a a judgment
based on records on books in Daniel
chapter 7. Intercession by a mediator
Esther as a type of
Christ. Condemnation of the wicked,
vindication of the
righteous. Come on
y'all. The feast of Purum originates
from the events of Shashan. Pyramid is a
celebration of deliverance and reversal
of faith from condemnation to
redemption.